Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- General Research Files, 1822-2002; Series IV; 31.4 linear feet (75 boxes)
  - Photography by Technique
    - Cased Photographs
      - Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection
        - Copy Photographs
          Copy photographs of cased photographs in Palmquist's collection, as well as other photographic material in his collection.
          - Ford, James May (Box 161)
          - Hamilton, Charles F. (Box 161)
          - Johnson, George Howard (Box 161)
          - Norcross, Oliver H. P. (Box 161)
          - Shaw & Johnson (Box 161)
          - Shew, Jacob (Box 161)
          - Shew, William (Box 161)
          - Vance, Robert H. (Box 161)
          - Unidentified photographers (Box 161)
          - Unidentified photographers, 14 folders (Box 162)
            This group of copy photographs chiefly documents cased photographs in Palmquist's collections, as well as groups of cartes-de-visite and cabinet photographs
        - Photographer Background Files
          Biographical information, photocopies of cased photographs, and other material related to photographers with work represented in the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection. Much of the content duplicates material in the collection inventories.
          - Allen, Charles V. (Box 163)
          - Balch, Eliza and Leland (Box 163)
          - Beardsley, B. C. (Box 163)
          - Boye, Otto H. (Box 163)
          - Broadbent, Samuel (Box 163)
          - Cary, Charles H. (Box 163)
          - Clayton, James Atkins (Box 163)
          - Cook, William H. (Box 163)
          - Coombs, Frederick C. (Box 163)
          - Culver & Fellows (Box 163)
          - Daniels, Austin F. (Box 163)
          - Fardon, George Robinson (Box 163)
          - Ford, James May (Box 163)
          - Gutekunst, Frederick (Box 163)
          - Hale, Luther Holman (Box 163)
          - Hamilton (Box 163)
          - Hamilton, Charles F. (Box 163)
          - Hamilton, D. (Box 163)
          - Hathaway, William N. (Box 163)
          - Hawes, Charles E. (Box 163)
          - Hickling, J. (Box 163)
          - Higgins, Thomas J. (Box 163)
          - Johnson, George Howard (Box 163)
          - "La Nina" (Box 163)
          - Lenox, Isaac Shaw (Box 163)
          - Marks (Box 163)
          - Maxham, Benjamin D. (Box 163)
          - McIntyre, Sterling C. (Box 163)
          - Norcross, Oliver H. P. (Box 163)
          - Phillips, J. A. (Box 163)
          - Pine, George W. (Box 163)
          - Plumbe, John Jr. (Box 163)
          - Quinby, Charles J. (Box 163)
          - Ramsaur, Malvina Antoinette (née Thompson) (Box 163)
          - Rehn, Isaac (Box 163)
          - Ritchie (Box 163)
          - Ruth, J. (Box 163)
          - Selleck, Silas Wright (Box 163)
          - Shaw, Seth Louis (Box 163)
          - Shew, Jacob (Box 163)
          - Shew, Myron (Box 163)
          - Shew, William (Box 163)
          - Silver, O. B. (Box 163)
          - Spooner Bros. (Box 163)
          - Spooner, John Pitcher (Box 163)
          - Vance, Robert H. (Box 163)
          - Whitehurst, Jesse Harrison (Box 163)
          - Wilde, Augusta (Box 163)
          - Willard, Oliver H. (Box 163)
          - Williams, Mrs. H. R. (Box 163)
          - Withington, Elizabeth W. (Box 163)
      - Literature Related to Daguerreotypes
        Exhibition catalogs, articles, and other works related to daguerreotypes.
        - "150 Years of Photography in Australia," Pro Talk, 1991 September (Box 164)
        - Alexander, Abel J., José Hernández o el daguerrotipo más curioso de la Argentina, 1991 (Box 164)
        - Alexander, Abel J., "La Magia del daguerrotipo," El Museo Historico Fotográphico de Quilmes, 1991 (Box 164)
        - "Digital Meets Daguerreotype: 150 years of Photography in Australia," Professional Photography in Australia, 1991 August (Box 164)
        - Cox, Robert Sayre, "Helios: Writing with Light at the Clemens Library," The Quarto, 1996 April (Box 164)
        - Ewer, Gary W., Reproductions of newspaper clippings about San Francisco daguerreotype photographers (Box 164)
        - Federación Argentina de Fotografía, 20 Congreso de Historia de la fotografía en la Argentina (1839-1939), 1993 (Box 164)
        - Harmon, Albert M., "Gold Rush Panoramas: The View from Nob Hill," San Francisco Maritime Museum, 1964 September (Box 164)
        - Harmon, Albert M., "Gold Rush Panoramas," Sea Letter, 1964 October (Box 164)
        - Isenburg, Matthew R., "The Art of the Daguerreotype," J. Paul Getty Museum, 1998 (Box 164)
        - Isenburg, Matthew R., The Making of a Daguerreotype, 2001 (Box 164)
        - Jakob, Volker, Menschen im Silberspiegel: die Anfänge der Fotografie in Westfalen, 1989 (Box 164)
        - Johnson, Brooks, "Mirror of an Era: The Daguerreotype in Virginia," Chrysler Museum (Box 164)
        - Johnson, Drew Heath, "Art and History," The Museum of California, 1994 December (Box 164)
        - Kessler, Mike, "Fred Stocking, His Bride, and Partners," The Photographist, 1984 Spring (Box 164)
        - Lee, Edward, "A Picture Perfect Partnership," Dealer World, 1989 April (Box 164)
          Article about daguerreotype collector Matthew R. Isenburg.
        - McCawley, Leigh, "The Silver Image: An Exhibition Commemorating Australia's First Photograph," Macleay Museum, 1991 (Box 164)
        - Oden, Lori, "Mirror Images: Daguerre and the First Photographic Process," International Photography Hall of Fame and Museum, 2001 (Box 164)
        - Owens, Gene, and Brian Woodward, "Double Feature: Two Views of Events that Celebrated 150 Years of Photography in Australia," Photographic Trader, 1989 (Box 164)
        - Robinson, Mike, "Flowers 2002: New Daguerreotypes", 2002 July (Box 164)
        - Shlaer, Robert, "Contemporary Daguerreotypes," Photo Eye Books & Prints (Box 164)
        - Weinstein, Robert A., San Francisco, 1851: A Sixty-Inch Panorama of the Bay of San Francisco, 1851, from Seven Daguerreotypes, 1970 (Box 164)
        - Wilson, Jackie Napolean and Weston Naef, "Hidden Witness: African Americans in Early Photography," J. Paul Getty Museum, 1995 (Box 164)
        - Wood, R. Derek, "The Voyage of Captain Lucas and the Daguerreotype to Sydney," NZ Journal of Photography, 1994 August (Box 164)
      - Copies of Cased Photographs
        Copy photographs and photocopies of cased photographs owned by repositories and individuals other than Palmquist.
        - American Antiquarian Society (Box 165)
        - American Hurrah Antiques (Box 165)
        - Bancroft Library (Box 165)
        - Belcher, David B. (Box 165)
        - Bokelberg Collection (Box 165)
        - Buberger, Joe (Box 165)
        - California Historical Society (Box 165)
        - California State Library (Box 165)
        - Cobb, Josephine (Box 165)
        - Daguerrian Forum (Box 165)
        - Daguerrian Society (Box 165)
        - Fisher (Box 165)
        - French, Greg Collection (Box 165)
        - Genzoli, Andre, Humboldt Room, Humboldt State University (Box 165)
        - George Eastman House (Box 165)
        - Gilman Paper Co. (Box 165)
        - Grabhorn, Edwin Collection (Box 165)
        - Hathaway Collection (Box 165)
        - Huntington (Box 165)
        - Isenberg Collection (Box 165)
        - Jaiquin (Box 165)
        - J. Paul Getty (Box 165)
        - Lerch, Ron (Box 165)
        - Metropolitan Museum of Art (Box 165)
        - Minnesota Historical Society (Box 165)
        - Museum of The History of Science (Box 165)
        - National Martitime Museum (Box 165)
        - National Museum of American Art (Box 165)
        - Nebraska State Historical Society (Box 165)
        - New York Historical Society (Box 165)
        - Oakland Museum (Box 165)
        - Ohio State University Rinhart Collection (Box 165)
        - Peck, Herb (Box 165)
        - Phillips, A. R., Jr. (Box 165)
        - Reede (Box 165)
        - Rex Stark Americana (Box 165)
        - San Francisco Maritime Museum (Box 165)
        - Shearer (Box 165)
        - Siskiyou County Museum (Box 165)
        - Society of California Pioneers (Box 165)
        - Sotheby's (Box 165)
        - Sutter's Fort State Historical Park (Box 165)
        - Swann Galleries (Box 165)
        - Thompson, Wilfred (Box 165)
        - Townsend Collection, University of Texas at Austin (Box 165)
        - University of New Mexico Art Museum (Box 165)
        - Walle, Leonard (Box 165)
        - Weinstein Collection (Box 165)
        - Wells Fargo Bank (Box 165)
        - Unidentified sources, 11 folders (Box 165)
      - The Daguerreian Annual Notes
        Volumes with material related to The Daguerreian Annual, a publication by members of the Daguerreian Society, often compiled and designed by Palmquist, which focuses on the study and appreciation of daguerreotypes and their creators. Palmquist designated these volumes " The Daguerreian Annual -- Notes"
        - 1990 (Box 166)
        - 1991 (Box 167)
        - 1992 (Box 168)
        - 1993 (Box 169)
    - Enameled Cards
      Reseach material and specimen examples of enameled photographs, which first appeared in the United States during the 1860s as a way to protect albumen photographs. The technique left the photograph with a thin transparent layer to protect the image, which imparted a glossy appearance.
      - Notes (Box 170)
      - Vintage prints (Box 170)
      - Copy photographs (Box 170)
      - Photocopies of articles, 21 folders (Box 170)
    - Photographs with Hand Coloring
      Reseach material related to nineteenth century photographs with hand coloring.
      - Notes, 2 folders (Box 171)
      - Bancroft Library (Box 171)
      - California Historical Society (Box 171)
      - Copy photographs, 2 folders (Box 171)
      - Peter Britt (Box 171)
      - Photocopies of articles, 34 folders (Box 171)
    - Panoramic Paintings and Panoramas
      Research material related to painted panoramas. Popular in the middle of the nineteenth century, panoramic paintings and models became a popular way to represent landscapes and historical events. The painted panoramas influenced the development of photography, in particular the creation of photographic panoramas that show a wide view produced by a panoramic camera or by joining photographs together.
      - Notes, 2 folders (Box 172)
      - Panoramas: A Register of Exhibitions (Box 172)
      - Photocopies of articles, 8 folders (Box 172)
    - Stereoscopic Photography and Stereographs
      Organized under two headings: Price Lists and Advertising, and Ephemera
      Reseach material related to chiefly related to historical and contemporary market for stereoscopic photography and stereographs.
      - Price Lists and Advertising
        Includes lists of stereographs for sale by individuals via auction.
        - 3-D Book Productions (Box 173)
        - 3-D Foto World (Box 173)
        - The 3-D Zone (Box 173)
        - Ginnis, Bryan W. (Box 173)
        - Griffith, Michael (Box 173)
        - Hoffman, Gordon D. (Box 173)
        - Maillet (Box 173)
        - McIntyre, Tim (Box 173)
        - National Stereoscopic Association (Box 173)
        - Parsons Technology (Box 173)
        - Reel 3-D Enterprises (Box 173)
        - Richard Link Photographics (Box 173)
        - Rinhart Galleries (Box 173)
        - Rowles, Brandt (Box 173)
        - S & D Enterprises (Box 173)
        - Saddy, John (Box 173)
        - Van Pelt, Charley (Box 173)
        - Vintage Cameras and Imagery (Box 173)
      - Ephemera
        - Carson, Andrew, "Stereopticon Collecting," The Mother Lode Antique Gazette, 1983 July (Box 173)
        - Grand Stereopticon Entertainment, ticket, circa 1885-1890 (Box 173)
        - Lovejoy & Foster, wholesale and retail dealers in stereoscopes and views, business card, circa 1875 (Box 173)
        - Oxy-Calc---, Stereopticon Exhibition, broadside, circa 1875-1885 (Box 173)
    - Photograph Buttons
      Material related to photograph buttons, a presentation technique with photographs mounted on a button mechanism that a wearer may temporarily fasten to the surface of a garment using a safety pin, or a pin formed from wire, a clutch, or other mechanism.
      - Palmquist, Peter E., "Button, Button, Who's Got the Photo Button," draft (Box 174)
      - Palmquist, Peter E., "The Cruver 'Photo-Medallion' Sales Kit," Photographica, 1979 November (Box 174)
      - Advertisements (Box 174)
      - Catalogs (Box 174)
      - Copy photographs (Box 174)
    - Photographic Techniques and Related Photographic Equipment
      Material related to a variety of photographic techniques and related equipment.
      - Advertising Cards (Box 175)
      - Autochromes (Box 175)
      - Cabinet photographs (Box 175)
      - Camera obscura (Box 175)
      - Cartes-de-visite backmarks (Box 175)
      - Cartes-de-visite album from Clovis, California (Box 175)
      - Large cameras, 4 folders (Box 175)
      - Printing out paper (Box 175)
      - Unusual photographs (Box 175)
  - Collected Historical Material
    Various historical material collected by Palmquist.
    - Beatty, Francis, St. Andrews, Philadelphia, letter to children, 1854 May 25 (Box 176)
    - Brownscombe, Jennie Augusta, Rome, Italy, letter to Julia H. Johnston, New Milford, Pennsylvania, and accompanying photographs, 1903 November 30 (Box 176)
    - Knopke, N. H., World War I ephemera (Box 176)
    - Morris, J. M., letter in color cipher to Sister Hatty, Minersville, California, 1863 December 30 (Box 176)
      Accompanied by a transcription and note from Harriet Tracy DeLong to Palmquist, January 18, 1989.
    - San Jose State College Little Theater, Broadside for "East Lynne", 1942 April (Box 176)
    - "The Story of My Life by Myself," amateur chapbook, circa 1910 (Box 176)
  - Mixed Research Files
    Organized by Palmquist's original order under two headings: First Group and Second Group.
    Two distinct groups of research files with material on various subjects related to Palquist's projects and interests.
    - First Group
      - Images on canvas (Box 177)
      - Traveling photographers and mobile darkrooms (Box 177)
      - California Miscellaneous No. 1-10, 10 folders (Box 177)
      - California on stone - Lithographs etc. (Box 177)
      - California miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 177)
      - Chinese (Box 177)
      - Photographers (Box 177)
      - Photographic jewelry (Box 177)
      - Photographer's studios (Box 177)
      - Photographer's trade cards (Box 177)
      - San Jose Project (Box 177)
      - Swedes (Box 177)
      - Tintypes (Box 177)
      - Stereographs and miscellaneous (Box 177)
      - Swedes, contact prints (Box 177)
      - Tracy Project (Box 177)
      - Vance R. H. and miscellaneous (Box 177)
      - Von Schneidau, Polycarpus (Box 177)
      - Watkins (Box 177)
      - Women photographers and miscellaneous (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous without negatives (Box 177)
    - Second Group
      - Alaska, trip to (Box 177)
      - Annual Project (Box 177)
      - Armer, Laura (Box 177)
      - Armer, Laura, sand paintings (Box 177)
      - Bonney, Therese (Box 177)
      - Daguerreotype and miscellaneous (Box 177)
      - D'Estrella, T. H. (Box 177)
      - Eldrige (Box 177)
      - Fardon, G. R. (Box 177)
      - Freeman, Edwin R. (Box 177)
      - Hickman (Box 177)
      - Howland, B. F., family (Box 177)
      - Kneeland Book (1871-1872) (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous - California, Early (Box 177)
      - Daguerreotypes (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous, Interesting (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous, Humboldt County (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous overland & sea travel to California (Box 177)
      - Music (Box 177)
      - Quincy Daguerreotypes (Box 177)
      - Behind the Redwood Curtain (Box 177)
      - Pacific Coast Photographer (Box 177)
      - Shaw, Seth Louis (Box 177)
      - Strong, N. B., negatives (Box 177)
      - Miscellaneous - Color negatives, Midwest, etc. (Box 177)
      - Daguerreotypes - Color negatives (Box 177)
      - Photo-Buttons - Color Negs (Box 177)
      - Daguerreotype - Adverts (Box 177)
      - Images from John Adams-Graf, In Rags for Riches: A Daguerreian Survey of Forty-Niners' Clothing (Box 177)
      - Siskiyou County (Box 177)
  - Card Files
    Manuscript and typescript card files related to projects, collections, and publications by Palmquist.
    - California city and state directories (Box 178)
    - California stereographs (Box 178)
    - Carleton Watkins research (Box 179)
    - Cartes-de-visite, enamel process (Box 178)
    - Early photographers in Arizona, Idaho, Nevada, and Utah (Box 178)
    - Humboldt County city and county directories (Box 178)
    - Index to photographers in Camera Craft, 1900-1901, published by the Photographers' Association of California (Box 178)
    - Northern California newspapers (Box 178)
    - Publications by Peter Palmquist (Box 180)
    - Robert Vance (Box 180)
    - San Francisco photographers in 1894 (Box 180)
    - Voices from the Craft (Box 180)
  - Research Material on Microfilm
    Microfilm of archival and printed material related to projects, collections, and publications by Palmquist.
    - Baker, Isaac W., Journals, 1849-1852 (Box 181)
      List of members of the Beverly Joint Stock San Francisco Company; record of voyage around the Horn on bark, San Francisco, Thomas Remmonds, Master; experiences in California, including the mines; return voyage, to Realejo on bark, Belgrade, and on steamer, Cherokee, from Chagres. Also, record of voyage from Boston on ship, John Q. Adams, sailing Aug. 8, 1852, and impressions of California. Many drawings throughout.
    - Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Western Americana, Frontier History of the Trans-Mississippi West, 1550-1900 (Box 181)
      Includes Oliver Jennings, Overland Journey from Oregon City (WA MSS 273)
    - Bush, Henry, The Harp of the Day, or, The Adventures and Travels of a Photographic Artist: With Other Poems (San Francisco: Printed for the author, 1865) (Box 181)
    - Coombs, Frederick, The Dawn of the Millennium! Splendid Discovery! A Beautiful Plan to Give Every Man (and Woman Also) a Nice House and Lot, and a Nice Little Wife or Husband for All, with Nearly One Hundred Pictorial Illustrations of Some Passages in the Life and Thrilling Adventures of the Author, Pioneer and Missionary of Science and Beneficence Around the World!! (New York: F. Coombs, 1869) (Box 181)
    - Dornin, George D., 1849-1879: Thirty Years Ago (1879) (Box 181)
    - Free Public Library (New Bedford, Mass.), Whaling Manuscripts, Numbers 3361-3369 (Box 181)
      Log books and diaries of whaling voyages in the collection of the Melville Whaling Room in the Free Public Library, New Bedford, Massachusetts. Includes the diary of photographer John Pitcher Spooner aboard the James R. Keeler, November 1863-April 1864.
    - Herman, William (pseudonym for Ambrose Bierce and Thomas A. Harcourt), The Dance of Death (San Francisco: Henry Keller, 1879) (Box 181)
      Photographer William Herman Rulofson financed the book.
    - Pacific Coast Photographer, Volumes 1-2 (Box 181)
    - Library of Congress, Prints and Photographs Division, Carleton Watkins, Photographic views of Kern County, California, 1888 (Lot 3379) (Box 181)
    - Sedgwick, S. J., Announcement of Prof. S. J. Sedgwick's Illustrated Course of Lectures and Catalogue of Stereoscopic Views of Scenery in All Parts of the Rocky and Sierra Nevada Mountains: Between Omaha and San Francisco (Newtown, New York: S. J. Sedgwick, 1879) (Box 181)
    - Taber, I. W., Catalogue, Alaska to Mexico: Pacific Coast Scenery: Views, Albums, Transparencies, Etc. (San Francisco: Taber, 1889) (Box 181)
    - United States v. D. & V. Peralta in United States, District Court, California Land Case ND 100, Land Court No. 4, depositions, 1861 (Box 181)
    - Yale University Library, Photograph album of views on the Pacific coast, British Columbia, circa 1870. (Box 181)
    - Yosemite National Park Research Library, Files on photographers J. T. Boysen and the Pillsbury Picture Company (Box 181)
  - Material Removed from Books
    Arranged alphabetically by subject or author.
    Material removed from books in the library of Palmquist after the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library acquired it.
    - American Indians (Box 182)
    - Arcata, California (Box 182)
    - Bearss, Edwin C. History Basic Data: Redwood National Park, Del Norte and Humboldt Counties, California, excerpts, 1982 (Box 182)
    - Brown, Dudley P., and family (Box 182)
    - Bruff, Joseph Goldborough (Box 182)
    - California maps (Box 182)
    - Crescent City, California (Box 182)
    - Deering, Clara (Box 182)
    - Dukes family (Box 182)
    - Fort Gaston, California (Box 182)
    - Foster, Seth B., Mrs. (Box 182)
    - Gasquet and Orleans (the G-O Road) (Box 182)
    - Gregg-Wood Expedition (Box 182)
    - Hammond, C. (Box 182)
    - Harris, C. C. (Box 182)
    - Harte, Bret (Box 182)
    - Hill, Thomas (Box 182)
    - Humboldt, Alexander von (Box 182)
    - Humboldt Bay, California, 2 folders (Box 182)
    - Humboldt County, California, early artists (Box 182)
    - Humboldt County, California, early photographs (Box 182)
    - Humboldt County, California, maps, 2 folders (Box 182)
    - Humboldt County, California, photographers, 1850-1940 (Box 182)
    - Humboldt County, California, general subjects (Box 182)
    - Humboldt Times newspaper (Box 182)
    - Kinman, Seth, 2 folders (Box 182)
    - Klamath, California (Box 182)
    - Klamath gold region (Box 182)
    - Massacre of American Indians in the Trinity Mountains, spring 1852 (Box 182)
    - McMurtie, W. B. (Box 182)
    - Pioneer School House, Eureka, California (Box 182)
    - San Francisco Journal of Commerce, Humboldt County Issue, 1888 November (Box 182)
    - Schumacher, Carl (Box 182)
    - Scotia, California (Box 182)
    - Shaw, Stephen William, and Seth Lewis Shaw (Box 182)
    - Shaw, Stephen William, Portrait of Wiyot elder Kiwelattah (or Ki-we-lah-tah) (Box 182)
    - Shipwrecks (Box 182)
    - Townsend, Edward Davis (Box 182)
    - Trinidad, California (Box 182)
    - Trinidad News and Views newspaper (Box 182)
    - United States Coast Survey in 1851 (Box 182)
    - Vance House (Box 182)
    - Weaverville, California (Box 182)
- Collection Inventories, 1985-1994; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Inventories for portions of Palmquist's collection of textual and photographic material documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its beginning through the turn of the twenty-first century.
  - Books by or about women photographers, 1994 August (Box 183)
  - Business directories (Box 183)
  - California business directories and gazetteers, 1994 August (Box 183)
  - Nineteenth century California photographers located in the files of Peter E. Palmquist, 1985 August; 3 folders (Box 183)
  - Non-California studio backmarks, 1994 August (Box 183)
  - Non-California correspondence and billheads, 1994 August (Box 183)
  - Non-California trade cards, 1994 August; 2 folders (Box 183)
  - Periodicals and California history journals, 1992 December 1 (Box 183)
  - Photographic catalogues and price lists, 1995 January; 2 folders (Box 183)
  - Photographs by Humboldt County photographers, undated (Box 183)
  - Photography magazines, serials, and annuals, 1993 January, 1994 February 1, 1997 December (Box 183)
  - Publications concerning photographic retouching and coloring, 1994 August; 2 folders (Box 183)
  - Traveling photographers, 1994 August; 2 folders (Box 183)
  - Vintage photographs by women in the Palmquist archive, 1994 August (Box 183)
- Business Records, 1962-1964; Series VI; 0.42; (1 box)
  Sales book and tax forms, as well as receipts chiefly for film and photographic processing, related to Palmquist's professional photography, 1962-1964.